<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="35"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[Key Points Note






                           ENGLISH
                           ENGLISH


                        LANGU
                                               A
                                                    GE
                        LANGUAGE

                                        for

                   JUNIOR SECONDARY SCHOOLS


                 Get the most out of the Fountain Key Points Notes Series.


                    The Facts  Just what you need to know.

                    Study & remember very quickly.


                    Revision questions are also included.






                  A REVISION GUIDE SERIES]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[1st Edition    2018


            ISBN  978 - 978 - 54914 - 5 - 6


            All our rights reserved. No part of this publication may be reproduced,
            stored in a retrieval system or transmitted in any form or by any means,
            electronic, mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise without the
            prior written permission of the copyright owner or the publisher.



            Published by

            Fountain of Grace Integrated Services Ltd (FOGIS)
            11B, Drive 4
            Prince & Princes Estate
            Abuja.

            +234 81-800-196-44
            +234 80-319-337-65

            info@fountainkeypoints.com
            fountainkeypoints@gmail.com

            www.fountainkeypoints.com




            ©
            Fountain of Grace Integrated Services Ltd
            2015]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[TABLE OF CONTENT

       PART ONE              (1  – 3)       PART FOUR             (14 – 26)
       -   READING                          GRAMMATICAL ACCURACY
       -   Reading  and  Understanding  a  -    Noun
           Passage                          -   Classification of Noun
       -   Scanning                         -   Grammatical Functions of Noun
       -   Skimming                         -   Pronoun
       -   Intensive Reading                -   Classes of Pronoun
       -   Use of Vocabulary                -   Verb
       -   Polysemy                         -   Adverbs
                                            -   Prepositions
                                            -   Adjectives
       PART TWO              (4  – 10)      -   Conjunctions
       WRITING (COMPOSITION)
       -   The Conventions Required
       -   Types of Composition             PART FIVE             (27 – 30)
       -   Elements of Composition          LITERATURE
       -   Letter Writing                   -   Prose
       -   Features of Informal Letter      -   Prose as Fiction
       -   Features of Formal Letter        -   Types of Fiction
       -   Features of Official/Business Letter  -  Prose as Non-fiction
       -   Essay Writing                    -   Characteristics of Prose
       -   The Narrative Essay              -   Drama
       -   The Argumentative Essay          -   Some Dramatic Elements
       -   The Descriptive Essay            -   Types of Drama
       -   The Expository Essay             -   Poetry
       -   Speech Writing                   -   Types of Poetry
       -   Summary Writing                  -   Elements of Poetry
                                            -   Figure of Speech

       PART THREE            (11 – 13)
       LISTENING/SPEAKING
       -   Vowel Sounds
       -   Diphthongs
       -   Consonant Sounds
       -   Rhyme
       -   Stress
       -   Intonation
       -   Question Tag
       -   Clusters]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[NOTE FROM THE FOUNTAIN KEY POINTS TEAM

        Fountain Keypoints have been carefully prepared to help students maximize their chances
        of succeeding in their examinations. The book covers the newly revised junior secondary
        school curriculum and uses a unique approach of bringing out key points required by
        examiners. Revision questions have also been included at the end of each part to test how
        much the reader understood the topics covered.

        The general reader will also find this book handy as a quick source of information and
        knowledge. Topics have been clearly presented in different parts to enable quick and easy
        reference.

        Candidates, students, teachers and the general public will definitely benefit from this book
        in different ways.]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART ONE
       READING                              Understanding, in reading, comes from
                                            the use of register, which is the technical
       Reading is one of the fundamental skills  use  of  vocabulary,  and  its  diverse
       of language. The fundamental skills of  nature.  We  have  sports  and
       language  are,  speaking,  writing,  entertainment register, political register,
       reading, and (now) listening. Note that  law  and  crime  register,  science  and
       before now, listening was not listed as a  technology register, and arts and culture
       fundamental skill of language because  register, and so on. The technical use of
       only  a  thin  line  separates  it  from  language  is  what  makes  a  passage
       speaking. The learning and acquisition  difficult to understand. Though we have
       of all the fundamental skills of language  general  use  of  language  or  general
       are what qualify the understanding of a  vocabulary,  if  words  with  general
       language.                            meanings are high sounding or complex
                                            words, a passage would be difficult to
       Reading, therefore, is a skill that enables  understand.
       a  person  to  decode  (understand)
       whatever is encoded (written) so long as  It is pertinent, therefore, to consider the
       what is written is in the letters or figures  tone and mood of any passage. These
       of  the  language  the  reader  learnt.  things would give the reader the overall
       Reading, at this level, goes beyond the  message of the passage. While mood is
       ability to identify letters or numbers but  the  feeling  of  the  writer,  tone  is  the
       involves  understanding  from  critical  understanding  a  student  gets  from
       evaluation. Thus,  one  may be  able  to  reading a passage.
       pronounce (or read) a combination of
       letters (a word), one may not be able to  SCANNING
       deduce  a  general  meaning  from  a  Scanning is a fast reading technique that
       passage. That is the crux of the matter  enables  the  students  read  for
       here.  To  gain  the  ability  to  read  and  information and interest. To scan, the
       understand  a  passage,  it  is  important  reader  goes  through  topic  sentences.
       that students understand the following:  What  is  topic  sentence?  It  is  the
                                            sentence that contains a major point in a
       READING AND UNDERSTANDING A  paragraph. Note that paragraph is a unit
       PASSAGE                              of composition that has a major point.
       Comprehension is the ability of a person  That  point  is  concentrated  in  one
       to  read,  listen  and  write  with  sentence  called  topic  sentence  and
       understanding. Thus, we have reading  expatriated in the remaining sentences
       c o m p r e h e n s i o n ,   l i s t e n i n g   known as supporting sentences. Going
       c o m p r e h e n s i o n   a n d   w r i t i n g   through  topic  sentences  only  in  a
       comprehension.  Since  we,  at  the  passage is another way of summarizing
       moment,  are  discussing  reading  the passage.
       comprehension, it is important we focus
       our attention on reading.

                                           1]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART ONE
       SKIMMING                             written work is the word. The more the
       This is another reading technique which  familiarity  of  words  in  a  passage  the
       entails reading for detail. When we skim,  easier  the  understanding.  We  advise
       we  read  for  implied  and  inferred  students  to  read  often  in  order  to
       meanings. Skimming is a technique we  improve their knowledge of vocabulary.
       cannot  sideline  in  critical  reading.
       Without details, how can we evaluate a  POLYSEMY
       passage and get understanding? So, the  One  other  thing  that  is  worthy  of
       reader reads between the line, makes  mention  is  polysemy.  There  are
       deduction and arrives at a conclusion.   dictionary and context meanings. Words
                                            that can be used alternatively, within a
       INTENSIVE READING                    context form polysemy. In the example:
       This kind of reading is slow and affords  'She  was  gradually  killed  while  she
       the student to make critical judgment.  listened  to  some  music  on  the  radio',
       He analyzes and criticizes a passage on  presents a context. If we single out the
       his own without any interference. Again,  word, 'killed', what word can replace it
       he makes deductions and, based on any  within  the  context?  The  meaning  of
       previous  knowledge,  forms  some  'killed' in the sentence is not 'murdered'.
       synthetic information. His  research, in  The word 'killed',  as it collocates with
       other words, is restricted to the passage  'music' cannot be 'murdered'. Thus, the
       in front of him. It is not an extensive  right choice would be 'thrilled'. Thus, if
       reading  that  involves  extensive  we replace the word, the sentence in the
       research.  The  reader  carries  out  his  example would read, 'She was gradually
       judgment based on the passage before  thrilled while she listened to some music
       him.                                 on  the  radio.'  So,  context  meaning
                                            should be taken into consideration when
       USE OF VOCABULARY                    we talk about word replacement.
       No extensive or continuous writing can
       take  place  without  the  use  of  EXERCISE
       vocabulary.  It  is  how  a  writer  uses
       vocabulary that either makes a written  Read the passages below and answer
       work  difficult  or  easy  to  understand.  the questions that follow.
       When  a  passage  contains  vocabulary
       that  is  difficult  to  understand,  it  is  Passage 1
       important that the reader finds out how   Breast  feeding  is  what  nursing
       the words in sentences collocate. Note  entails.  Every  mother  with  an  infant
       that  collocation  is  the  meaningful  baby must breast feed the baby for its
       combination of words. Thus, words with  well-being.  An  infant  baby's  digestive
       similar or different meanings are used in  system is such that allows  liquid food
       a  sentence  for  a  purpose.  When  the  until the baby grow to a stage where its
       reader notes how words collocate, then,  parent  naturally  introduces  semi-solid
       the entire meaning of the sentence will  food to the baby.
       be  easy.  The  key  to  understanding  a   For fast mental growth, nutritionists
                                           2]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART ONE
       and doctors alike, have advised strongly  error  like  premarital  sex  and  or
       that mothers carry out exclusive breast  pregnancy blots out a parent's dream for
       feeding.  What  is  exclusive  breast  that child?
       feeding?  Exclusive  breast  feeding  is   Premarital sex is prevalent among
       breast  feeding  activity,  between  a  teenagers  today.  It  is  common
       mother  and  her  baby,  that  excludes  knowledge  many  mothers,  who
       additives to the baby's meal, including  themselves lack moral fibres encourage
       water.  Thus,  when  a  mother  does  their daughters to have boyfriends. To
       exclusive  breast  feeding,  she  is  them it is an acceptable social behavior.
       expected  not  to  give  the  baby  even  But they fail to give their daughter the
       water.  The  baby's  whole  food  is  the  needed  sex  education  with  the  single
       breast milk.                         objective of abstinence. Some parents
           Why do medical experts make such  are strict, very strict, but they also fail to
       recommendation?  Exclusive  breast  give their daughters sex education that
       feeding  help  the  baby  to  develop  would enable them become conscious of
       immunity against common diseases that  consequences  of  premarital  sex.  The
       claim the lives of infants. It contributes  media  are  the  biggest  culprit.  The
       to  a  high  mental  development  of  the  countless unedited videos uploaded into
       infant  later  in  life.  Exclusive  breast  the internet is a brazen but very wrong
       feeding is responsible for a baby's good  attitude from the service providers. If a
       health and strength.                 parent prohibits a child from watching
       1. What is exclusive breast feeding?   movies on TV or from using the phone,
       2. Who recommended it?               without any convincing reason, the child
       3. Have  women  been  applying  the  becomes curious. It would not take long
           method?                          before the child gets to watch certain
       4. What  is  the  other  breast  feeding  prohibitive videos on a friend's phone, a
           method called?                   friend whose parents may not be strict
       5. State  the  importance  of  exclusive  after all. Such videos have effects that
           breast feeding.                  hook the users on until it becomes too
                                            late.
       Passage 2                                Premarital  sex  leads  to  aborted
           The desire of every parent for his  dreams and such dire consequence like
       son  or  daughter  is  to  succeed  in  life.  premarital pregnancy, death or suicide.
       Only few parents, very few parents, do  1. What is premarital sex?
       not  support  the  dream  that  their  2. What  age  bracket  is  it  common
       children should become more successful   with?
       or more important in life than them. This  3. What effort do parents make to curb
       explains  why  many  parents  endure     the menace?
       hardship and work hard to see to the  4. Mention  some  consequences  of
       fulfillment  of  their  desire.  How  happy   premarital sex.
       they are when their children succeed in  5. Do  you  think  we  can  control  or
       life  and  become  responsible  people.   regulate the activities of the media?
       What  happens,  however,  when  one
                                           3]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART TWO
       WRITING (COMPOSITION)                LETTER WRITING
                                            Letter  writing  is  the  oldest  form  of
       Composition means continuous writing.  transmitting information by one party to
       Writing is a skill, like reading, that can be  another party. There are two (2) major
       developed through consistent practice.  kinds of letter – the informal letter and
       Besides  reading, writing  is  a  skill  that  the formal letter.
       determines  a  person's  level  of
       education. At this level, we shall discuss  FEATURES OF INFORMAL LETTER
       writing  in  the  introductory  phase.  -  Address
       However, we shall do indepth analysis of  -  Date
       writing.                             -   Salutation
                                            -   Introduction (or opening)
       THE CONVENTIONS REQUIRED             -   Body (the message)
       These are elements that make a piece of  -  Conclusion
       written  work;  an  article,  an  essay,  a  -  Complimentary close.
       letter  or  a  book,  acceptable.  The
       conventions  used  in  writing  have  THE ADDRESS
       general acceptance, so that a good book  Every  informal  letter  has  only  one
       written by a Nigerian could be read by  address. Note that it is a type of letter we
       anyone who understands English in any  write to our dad, mum, brother, sister,
       part of the world. If the book falls short  cousin, friend, etc.
       of  standard,  say,  it  defies  standard
       conventions  for  writing,  then,  no  one  There  are  two  ways  of  arranging  the
       would  understand  the  book  which  address of an informal letter: the block
       hardly  makes  any  sense.  Standard  form and the slant form. Either of them
       conventions for writing are right choice  is acceptable.
       of  words,  correct  spelling,  good
       sentence  order,  correct  use  of  Examples:
       punctuations and orderly or sequential  -  Block form of address
       paragraphing.
                                                Holy Rosary College,
       TYPES OF COMPOSITION                     Adoka,
           Letter
       ¾writing                                 P.M.B. 2011,

       ¾writing                                 Otukpo Local Government Area,
           Essay

           Speech
       ¾writing                                 Benue State.

       ¾Summary writing

                                            -   Slant form of address
       ELEMENTS OF COMPOSITION
       Every standard composition is made up    Holy Rosary College,
       of  three  (3)  main  parts,  namely:             Adoka,
       introduction, body and conclusion. Let                 P.M.B. 2011,
                                                              Otukpo Local Government Area,
       us  discuss  the  types  of  composition
       listed above.                                        Benue State.
                                           4]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART TWO
                                            informal letter is that it also states the
       Note  that  the  writer's  name  must  not  purpose of the letter. An example will be
       appear at the top of the address. Again,  shown in a letter sample later.
       you can use punctuations in the address
       or leave it unpunctuated. In the informal  THE BODY
       letter, abbreviations are allowed.   The  body  of  any  letter  contains  the
                                            message  in  detail.  It  is  segmented  in
       THE DATE                             paragraphs  –  each  paragraph  must
       Date is used to show when a letter is  contain a distinct or separate idea. The
       written. We have the cardinal date form  ideas that make up the body of a letter
       and the ordinal date form.           are  sub-themes  and  should  not  be
                                            clumped up together in one paragraph.
       Examples:                            Each  paragraph  should  begin  with  a
       -   Cardinal date                    topic  sentence  which  consists  of  the
           22nd July, 2017.                 main  idea  in  that  paragraph.  See  the
                                            sample letter.
       -   Ordinal date
           July 22, 2017.                   THE CONCLUSION
                                            The  conclusion  of  an  informal  letter
       Note the differences in the positions of  gives the writer the opportunity to draw
       the day and the month. Both of them are  a needed lesson he wants the recipient
       acceptable.  Please,  avoid  writing  date  to learn. It also affords the writer the
       like  this:  22/07/2017,  when  writing  a  opportunity to bid the recipient farewell.
       letter.
                                            COMPLIMENTARY CLOSE
                                            This part of a letter, brings the letter to a
       SALUTATION                           close. It may take any of the following
       What follows the date under the address  forms (only  in  informal  letters): Yours
       is  salutation.  Salutation  is  an  Sincerely,  Yours  Ever,  Your  dad,  Your
       affectionate way of getting a person's  daughter, Your friend, etc. Note that a
       attention.  In  an  informal  letter,  signature is not needed and the writer is
       salutation may take any of the following  free to use his first name or pet name.
       ways: Dear friend, My dear friend, Dear
       Dad, My dear dad, etc. Note the comma
       that follows it.

       THE INTRODUCTION OR OPENING
       The opening or introduction is the first
       paragraph  and  follows  the  salutation
       immediately. The importance of this is to
       conclude the greeting or salutation that
       is  begun  with  the  word,  'Dear'.  The
       second importance of the opening of an
                                           5]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART TWO
                                   SAMPLE LETTER

       Write a letter to your friend in another school and tell him three (3) things about
       your school. Your letter must be 300 words long.

                                           Government Day Secondary School
                                                Gwarinpa,
                                                   P.M.B. 207,
                                                  Life-Camp,
                                                       F.C.T. Abuja.
                                                           22nd July, 2017

       Dear Friend,

           It's been a while since the last time I heard from you. I hope you're doing well in
       your studies. I'm not doing badly, in fact, I'm doing wonderfully well. I need you to
       know some great facts about my school.
           The quality of teaching is where I wish to begin. The quality of teaching is near
       perfect  because  our  teachers  teach  with  passion.  They  show  interest  in  their
       students and patiently teach them for understanding. Do you know that it has
       become the norm for the teachers to repeat lessons again and again because they
       want every student in class to understand. They are not harsh and hardly lose their
       temper when a student asks a question.
           My school has excellent and up-to-date facilities for learning. The classrooms
       are quite conducive and not crowded. There are twenty-five students in each class.
       Each student has a seat to himself and we use the white marker-board. It may
       interest you to know that each classroom is equipped with two air-conditioners for
       students'  comfort.  Again,  our  laboratories  (Physics,  Biology,  Computer
       Laboratories) are reasons why many students choose to study science subjects.
       They school's library can boast of modern books in its orderly catalogues.
           We have a standard football field, a standard volley ball court, an enviable
       basketball court and indoor sporting facilities that make sports interesting. Every
       evening,  students  simply  make  their  choice  of  sports  to  keep  body  and  soul
       together. I wish you were here with me.
           Well, I could go on and on but the time is not there for me to include everything
       my school has in this letter. I look forward to hearing from you soon. So long now.

                                                          Your friend,

                                                          Adole

       Note that the language used in informal letters is informal English. Therefore,
       expressions allow contraction (it's, isn't, you're, etc).
                                           6]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART TWO
       FEATURES OF FORMAL LETTER            FEATURES  OF  OFFICIAL/BUSINESS
       The formal letter is made up of two (2)   LETTER
       types,  namely:  semi-formal  letter  and   Every  official  or  business  letter  has
       official  or  business  letter.  Study  the   unique features:
       features of the semi-formal letter below.   -  Address (there are two addresses,
       -   Address  (only  one  address  is     the  writer's  address  and  the
           allowed)                             addressee's address)
       -   Date                             -   Date
       -   Salutation (often allows use of titles   -  Salutation
           before recipient's name) – Dear Dr.   -  Title
           Uche,                            -   Introduction
       -   Introduction/opening             -   Body
       -   Body                             -   Conclusion
       -   Conclusion                       -   Close
       -   Close  (the  close  is  usually,  Yours
           Sincerely,  followed  by  the  writer's
           signature  and  the  writer's  full
           name).
       Note  that  a  letter  written  to  one's
       teacher, an uncle, an aunt, etc, is a semi-
       formal letter.































                                           7]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART TWO
                                   SAMPLE LETTER

       Write a letter of employment to the post master of a post office for the post of a
       clerk. Your letter must be 300 words long.

                                                  Senior Secondary School,
                                                  Post Mail Box II,
                                                  Area 10, Garki,
                                                  Federal Capital Territory, Abuja.
                                                  22nd July, 2017.

       The Post Master,
       Garki Post Office,
       Area 10, Garki,
       Federal Capital Territory,
       Abuja.


       Dear Sir,
                       LETTER OF APPLICATION FOR A CLERK


           Sequel to your advert for a clerk in your post office, I write to indicate my
       interest in the position advertised in some national dailies. I am sixteen years old
       and I have the West African School Certificate (WASC). I passed all the subjects I sat
       for in distinction but because I do not have the needed money to further my
       education, I wish to work for two years and raise the money before furthering my
       education.
           Sir, I am a humble and hardworking boy and I believe you will not regret it if you
       employ me. I live with my uncle at Area 10, near the post office and so, I shall always
       be punctual at work. I work very well in the absence of any pressure or supervision.
       A copy of my curriculum vitae is attached to this application.
           I look forward to hearing from you soon. I pray for God's guidance when you do
       the selection of candidates for the interview.

                                                          Yours faithfully,

                                                          Haruna Ibro



       Note the various features of the letter above. They are what make the official letter
       different from other letter types. Remember, contractions or informal expressions
       are not allowed in official letters.

                                           8]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART TWO
       ESSAY WRITING                        Conclusion
                                            The last paragraph of an essay is the
       Essay  writing  is  another  form  of   concluding  paragraph.  Just  as  the
       composition. There are various types of   introductory  paragraph  introduces  an
       essay:  narrative,  argumentative,   essay, so does the concluding paragraph
       descriptive and expository essays.   bring it to an end.

       THE NARRATIVE ESSAY                  THE ARGUMENTATIVE ESSAY
       This type of essay tells a story. Although   This type of essay is persuasive. Usually,
       every  composition  type  has  the   two opposing ideas are introduced, as is
       characteristics  of  narration,  the   in a debate, through persuasion a writer
       narrative lays emphasis on events, past   should  be  able  to  convince  a  reader
       or  present  events.  When  a  student  is   which  of  the  two  ideas  is  better.  One
       asked to write about an incident, such   good characteristic of this essay is that
       essay is a narrative essay. Consider the   the verbs are in the present tense. Each
       following features of the narrative essay.   paragraph, as a matter of rule, should
                                            begin with a topic sentence. Note that
       Title                                the  features  discussed  under  the
       Every essay must have a title. Suppose   narrative  essay  are  the  same  as  the
       you are asked to write about a birthday   argumentative.
       party you attended recently, what would
       be your essay title? A BIRTHDAY PARTY   THE DESCRIPTIVE ESSAY
       or 'AN UNFORGOTTABLE DAY' would be   This essay describes a person, an event,
       acceptable. Note that if the title of your   a place or an animal. It is important to
       essay  is  in  capital  letters,  you  do  not   use adverbs and adjectives a lot when
       need to underline it except it is in the   writing the descriptive essay.
       lowercase. An essay title should not be
       long but short and concise.          THE EXPOSITORY ESSAY
                                            This essay exposes an unknown thing,
       Introduction                         like, tradition or custom. It is informative
       This is the first paragraph of an essay. In   and  educative  in  content  because  it
       this paragraph, the writer should be able   reveals what the reader does not know
       to  state  what  the  essay  is  all  about.   anything about.
       Here,  the  subject  matter  should  be
       explained briefly.
                                                    SPEECH WRITING
       Body                                 Speech writing is a little different from
       The body of an essay contains different   the  essay  in  the  sense  that  it  is  a
       paragraphs.  Each  paragraph  should   welcome  address.  Consider  the
       contain an idea (sub-theme) that makes   following features of speech writing.

       the subject matter. Learn to make the
       first  sentence  of  a  paragraph  a  topic
       sentence.
                                           9]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART TWO
       Title:                               Conclusion:
       The  event  or  occasion  is  highlighted  This paragraph concludes a speech in a
       here and the name and position of the  satisfactory way.
       person delivering the address are also
       included in the title, for instance:        SUMMARY WRITING
                                            In the senior secondary school syllabus
           AN ADDRESS PRESENTED BY JANET  or  curriculum,  this  is  not  discussed
           AGU,  THE  SENIOR  PREFECT  OF  under  composition.  Summary  writing
           GOVERNMENT  S ECOND ARY   means  paraphrasing,  reducing,
           SCHOOL,  DUTSEN-ALHAJI,  TO  according  to  relevant  points  available,
           MARK THE GRAND FINALE OF THE  the body length of an original passage or
           SCHOOL'S  INTER-HOUSE  SPORTS  work.  The  most  important  aspect  of
           COMPETITION                      summary is the topic sentence in each
                                            paragraph.  Locate  topic  sentences,
       Address:                             reduce  them  by  throwing  away
       The  address  of  any  speech  is  quite  irrelevant  illustrations  and  examples.
       different  from  the  address  of  a  letter.  Consider the following:
       While  the  address  of  a  letter  lays  -  In  summary  writing,  handwriting
       emphasis on the location of the person,   must be clear and legible.
       the address of any speech salutes the  -  Do  not  include  illustrations  and
       guests present. For instance             examples.
                                            -   Do not do dirty work.
              The Honourable Minister of Sports,  -  Locate  and  use  topic  sentences
           The Principal,                       accurately.
           Principals  Vice  Admin  and  Vice   -  Do not misspell words.
           Academics                        -   Use punctuations correctly.
           Distinguished Teachers,          -   Avoid copying or lifting – word for
           Guardians and Parents,
           Journalists and Other Guests,        word  –  from  an  original  passage.
           Fellow Students,                     Use your own words.
           Ladies and Gentlemen,
                                            EXERCISE
       The Introduction:                    1. Write a letter to your uncle who lives
       The  salutation  continues  into  the    in London and inform him of your
       opening paragraph of the speech. It also   sister's planned wedding.
       welcomes those present.              2. Write an essay on an unforgettable
                                                day.
       The Body:                            3. As the senior prefect of your school,
       The body of any speech is broken down    write a welcome address in honour
       into  segments  or  paragraphs,  each    of a visiting minister to your school.
       paragraph  detailing  a  challenge  or  4. Write  a  letter  to  your  dad  and
       progress,  depending  on  the  tone  the   request  five  things  you  need  in
       writer wants to give the speech.         school.

                                          10]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART THREE
       LISTENING/SPEAKING                   -   /r/ ram, rate
       Speech in English Language is made of  -  /l/ lose, lamp
       two parts, vowel and consonant parts.  -  /d/ dam, dean
       While  vowel  sounds  are  soft  and  -  /m/ mane, mat
       articulated  without  friction,  consonant  -  /n/ net, knot
       sounds are produced or articulated with  -  /̃/ sing, blink
       friction.                            -   /k/ chemical, kettle
                                            -   /?/ father, the
       Vowel Sounds                         -   /è/ theory, thick
       -   Monopthongs/Pure vowels          -   /z/ zebra, kids
       -   Short vowel /I/ e.g. sit, pick   -   /S/ sharp, shelter
       -   Long vowel /i:/ e.g. seat, peak  -   /ts/ church, chart
       -                 /e/ e.g. ten, pen  -   /d?/ germ, jealous
       -   Short vowel /æ/ fat, man         -   /?/ measure, leisure
       -   Long vowel /a:/ fart, harm       -   /v/ van, nephew
       -   Short vowel /o/ lot, rob         -   /f/ fence, physical
       -   Long vowel /?:/ born, corn       -   /j/ yellow, dispute
       -   Short vowel /? / put, look       -   /w/ we, when
       -   Long vowel /u:/ spoon, moon
       -                /^/ husband, love   Rhyme
       -                /3:/ turn, girl     When two words are pronounced in the
       -                /˷/ ago, around
                                            same way, we say they rhyme. There are
                                            complete rhyme, such as in, bee and be
       Diphthongs                           (the  long  and  short  sounds,  not
       -   /aI/ five, nine                  withstanding)  and  partial  rhyme.  In
       -   /a? / how, now                   partial rhyme, either the vowel sounds
       -   /eI/ made, today                 in  two  words  rhyme  or  only  the
       -   /ea/ air, tear (verb)            consonant sounds rhyme. Consider the
       -   /I˷/ near, tear, (nounc)
                                            following:
       -   /?I/ boy, noise                      Fart      Dart
       -   /˷? / no, dispose                    Lack      Tack
       -   /? ˷/ pure, cure                     Piece     Peace (complete rhyme)
                                                Spoon     Stool
       Consonant Sounds                         Can       Tan
       There are 24 consonant sounds. They      Toil      Coil
       are listed below:                        Span      Scan
       -   /b/ be, baby                         Lose      Loose
       -   /p/ pale, peace                      Cool      Tool
       -   /t/ tea, tame                        Moon      Noon
       -   /s/ sound, sea                       Womb      Tomb
       -   /h/ harm, heat                       Cost      Lost
       -   /g/ game, goose                      Boss      Loss

                                          11]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART THREE
       Stress                               following examples:
       Stress  means  emphasis  placed  on  a  -  I am a student, am I not? (or aint I?)
       syllable of a word. Every word has only  -  You're a pastor, aren't you?
       one primary stress. Between a primary  -  The day is bright, isn't it?
       stress  and  a  secondary  stress,  the  -  You're my friend, aren't you?
       primary stress is more important. In the  -  We are neighbours, aren't we?
       following  examples,  the  stressed  -   You have a book, haven't you?
       syllable is in the capital letter form.   -  She hasn't a book, has she?
                                            -   We  haven't  met  for  a  long  time,
       Verb                  Noun               have we?
       com-PLAIN             COM-plaint
       com-FORT              COM-fort       Clusters
       dis-TRESS             DIS-tress      Here,  we  shall  give  attention  to
       in-CREASE             IN-crease      consonant clusters only. We have initial,
       de-CREASE             DE-crease      mid and final clusters.
       im-PORT               IM-port
       ex-PORT               EX-port        Initial Cluster
                                            This cluster occurs in the beginning of a
       Intonation                           word.  Note  that  cluster  is  the
       English  is  spoken  with  a  rise  and  fall  combination of letters in pronunciation.
       tone.  Words  that  are  stressed  in  a  Consider the following examples:
       sentence are nouns, verbs (main verbs),  Programme   [pr]
       adverbs and adjectives. For instance, I  Stress    [str]
       AM  a  STUdent.  YOU  ARE  a  SEnator.  Broom      [br]
       Usually, the tone of the voice rises on a  Train   [tr]
       stressed word but falls on a word that is  Strain  [str]
       not  stressed.  When  a  statement  is  Cross      [cr]
       made, the tone of the voice usually falls
       in the last word. But when a question is  Mid cluster
       asked, especially, if it is a question that  This cluster occurs in the middle of  a
       needs a yes or no answer, then the tone  word
       of the voice rises in the last word.   Programme [gr]
                                            Problem [br]
       Question Tag                         Heterogeneity [tr]
       In the senior secondary school syllabus,  Reproduce [pr]
       this  topic  is  discussed  in  language  Reckless [kl]
       structure.  Question  tag  is  a  question
       that follows a statement in a sentence.   Final cluster
                                            This cluster occurs at the end of a word.
       There are two rules that guide question  Probable [bl]
       tag; a positive statement agrees with a  Ask [sk]
       negative tag and a negative statement  Baske [sk]
       agrees with a positive tag. Consider the  Battle [ttle]
                                          12]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART THREE
       Baffle [ffl]                         v.  spot
       Niddle [ddl]                             a)  spat
       Tackle [kl]                              b)  shot
                                                c)  pout
                                                d)  loud
       EXERCISE
                                            3. Identify the word that has the sound
       1. Underline the initial cluster in each   shown:
           word below:                          i.  /k/
           threat                                  a)  schedule
           grow                                    b)  chart
           plan                                    c)  chemist
           blame                                   d)  chill
           treat
           strand                               ii.  /z/
           produce                                 a) kids
                                                   b)  send
       2. Choose the word that has the same        c)  absent
           vowel sound as the word shown:          d)  sing
           i.  Peace
              a) spice                          iii. /d?/
              b) pass                              a)  gist
              c)  tease                            b)  game
              d)  pit                              c)  leisure
                                                   d)  measure
           ii.  tat
              a) loud                           iv. /?/
              b)  hound                            a)  equation
              c) bat                               b)  nation
              d)  snout                            c)  zebra
                                                   d)  nature
           iii. dove
              a)  money                         v.  /̃/
              b)  stove                            a)  mingle
              c)  note                             b)  knot
              d)  about                            c)  net
                                                   d)  noble
           iv. noun
              a)  band
              b)  cow
              c)  bind
              d)  find

                                          13]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART FOUR
       GRAMMATICAL ACCURACY                 -   Collective Nouns: Nouns that we
       In this part of the book, we shall focus   use in pairs or groups are collective
       our attention on parts of speech; their   in nature and, so, are used in one
       meanings and functions, tenses, active   sense. For example, a pair of shoes
       and  passive  forms  of  verbs,  transitive   (two shoes), a pair of sandals (two
       and intransitive verbs and some modal    sandals), a pair of keys, a bunch of
       auxiliaries.                             keys, a bouquet of flowers, a pair of
                                                scissors, a bevy of ladies, a class of
       Nothing much will be done on sentence    students,  a  congregation  of
       formation and parts of sentence. Those   worshippers, an army of soldiers, a
       are  well  dealt  with  in  the  senior   school of fish, a college of bishops,
       secondary work scheme.                   an army of ants, a swarm of bees, a
                                                flock of sheep, a gang of robbers, a
       NOUN                                     flock  of  birds,  a  fleet  of
       Noun  means  name;  the  name  give      cars/ship/aircraft,  a  band  of
       things, animals, places, persons, days of   musicians, a catalogue of or library
       the week, months of the year, etc.       of books, a team of players, etc.

       CLASSIFICATION OF NOUN               -   Quality Nouns: These nouns are
       Nouns are broadly classified into two (2)   so  called  because  they  are  about
       parts,  namely;  common  nouns  and      quality.  For  example,  gentility,
       proper  nouns.  They  are  discussed     simplicity,  meekness,  ugliness,
       below:                                   beauty, handsomeness, brightness,
                                                coldness, darkness, etc. it is safe to
       Common Nouns                             state  that  some  adjectives  are
       These  are  nouns  that  are  also  called   formed from quality nouns.
       general nouns. This is because they are
       general  names  of  things  and  animals.  EXERCISE
       They  are  sub-classified  into  the  1. Underline the common nouns used
       following:                               in the following sentences:
       -   Concrete  Nouns:  These  are         a) She  won  the  competition
           nouns,  or  simply,  names  given  to   because  of  her  beauty.
           things we can see and or touch. For   b) The  boy  screamed  when  he
           example,  stone,  house,  rock,  car,   mistakenly  kicked  against  a
           clothes, cloths, chair, bed, etc.       rock instead of the ball.
                                                c) A bevy of ladies sang their way
       -   Abstract  Nouns:  The  name  we         to the National Assembly.
           give,  things  or  ideas,  since  we   d) He said he had high hopes that
           cannot see them is abstract noun.       things would improve.
           They  are  abstract  because  we     e) The arrested thief claimed that
           cannot see them or touch them. For      hunger led him into stealing.
           example,  hunger,  hope,  faith,  air,
           wind, spirit, emotion, etc.
                                          14]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART FOUR
       Proper Nouns                         -   Names of months of the year:
       These nouns a specific names of things,   January,  March,  June,  August,
       places,  animals,  organizations  and    December, etc.
       persons.  Study  the  classes  of  proper
       nouns below:                         Note that a proper noun must begin with
                                            the capital letter, no matter its position in
       -   Specific  names  of  persons:  a sentence. Again, if a common noun is
           Juliet,  Mary,  Audu,  John,  used like a proper noun in a sentence, it
           Magdalene, Reuben, Danjuma, etc.   should  begin  with  a  capital  letter.  For
                                            example,  our  dad  gave  Mum  some
       -   Special  names  of  animals:  money.
           Bingo, Shelly, Tiger, etc. Note that
           the 'Tiger' in the example is not the
           wild  cat  as  it  is  a  common  noun
           which begins with a small letter 't'.  EXERCISE
           Tiger, here, is a name some people
           give their dog and as such, it must  Identify  the  proper  nouns  in  the
           begin with the capital letter 'T'.   sentences below:
                                            a) I  know  Dad  will  not  allow  me
       -   Specific names of places: Abuja,     accompany my friends.
           London,  Lagos,  Onitsha,  Kano,
           Sokoto, etc.                     b) We left home on Tuesday last week.
       -   Names  of  days  of  the  week:  c) Emeka, my friend, lives in Onitsha
           Sunday,  Monday,  Tuesday,           with his family.
           Wednesday,  Thursday,  Friday  and
           Saturday.                        d) I love Bimbo because she is honest.

       -   Names  of  organization  and  e) God lives to answer prayers so long
           companies: Julius Berger, Dantata    they are offered in accordance with
           & Sawoe, Central Bank of Nigeria,    His will.
           Pace-setters' College, etc.
















                                          15]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART FOUR
       Number and Gender of Nouns           Uncountable nouns do not have singular
                                            and plural form, though they are used
       Number                               with partitives sometimes, e.g. he gave
       When number is mentioned in grammar,   me some information. Note that 'some'
       it  refers  to  the  countable  and   does not, in any way, make information
       uncountable  nouns.  Nouns  that  are   a  countable  noun.  Consider  the
       countable  have  distinct  features  that   following examples of countable nouns.
       separate  them  from  uncountable  or
       nouns  that  cannot  be  counted.    Information,  infrastructure,  advice,
       Countable nouns are singular and plural   news, equipment, oil, water, air, sleep,
       in nature. Study the examples of nouns   etc. If we can say, 'much information',
       on the table below:                  'much sleep', 'much water' and so on,
                                            we can also use the partitive 'some' with
       Singular              Plural         uncountable nouns to mean, much, in
       Baby                  Babies         quantity,  not  in  number.  For  instance,
       Woman                 Women          some infrastructure, some advice, some
       Man                   Men            sleep, some water, etc.
       Chair                 Chairs
       Bench                 Benches        Gender
       Stadium               Stadia         Gender refers to the sex of an individual
       Leaf                  Leaves         or animal. In nouns, gender is used to
       Millennium            Millennia      differentiate between male and female
       Phenomenon            Phenomena      so  that  we  know  the  right  pronoun
       Cilium                Cilia          antecedent to apply with them.
       Ovum                  Ova
       Person                Persons        Male          Female
       Book                  Books          Man           Woman
       Boy                   Boys           Lion          Lioness
       Girl                  Girls          Tiger         Tigress
       Bag                   Bags           Ram           Ewe
       Phone                 Phones         Gander        Goose
       Hoe                   Hoes           Gentleman     Lady
       Singer                Singers        Boy           Girl
       Pot                   Pots
       Paper                 Papers
       Hill                  Hills
       Mountain              Mountains
       Language              Languages
       Ball                  Balls
       Footballer            Footballers




                                          16]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART FOUR
       EXERCISE 1                           Grammatical Functions of Noun
                                            The grammatical functions of noun are
       Identify the countable and uncountable  the  various  ways  nouns  are  used  in
       nouns used in the following sentences:  sentences.  The  following  are  some  of
                                            the functions of noun.
       a) Dele takes much water after meal.
                                            -   Noun  is  subject  of  verb  or
       b) Only few students turned up for the   sentence: When noun is used as
           test.                                subject of sentence, it is the head of
                                                that  sentence,  it  is  the  most
       c)  He  gave  me  little  information    important part of the sentence, e.g.
           yesterday.                           Jacob is a farmer. If our emphasis –
                                                which is – on Jacob, then Jacob is
       d) Julius  Berger  boasts  of  much      the  head  of  the  sentence,  hence,
           equipment in its yard.               subject of the sentence.

       e) Some city dwellers suffer a lot from   Yemisi is a girl. (Yemisi is the subject
           lack of infrastructure.              of the sentence).

                                                School has resumed. (School is the
       EXERCISE 2                               subject of the sentence).

       Use each of the following in sentences of   My pen is beautiful. (My pen is the
       your own:                                subject of the sentence).
       -   Lioness
       -   Hen                                  Note: The subject of any sentence
       -   Cock                                 is the subject of discussion in the
       -   Policewoman                          sentence.
       -   Priestess
       -   Princess                         -   Noun  is  object  of  verb:  When
       -   Lady                                 noun is used as object of verb, it is
       -   Priest                               either in the subject case form or in
       -   Gander                               the object case form. For instance,
                                                we can either say, 'We gave Jacob
                                                some  presents'  or  'We  gave  him
                                                some presents.' The first example
                                                shows  'Jacob'  in  the  subject  form
                                                but in the second example, 'Jacob' is
                                                in the object form 'him'.

                                                More examples:
                                                a) I told Olu the truth. ('Olu' is the
                                                   object of the verb 'told').
                                          17]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART FOUR
           b) Okocha  kicked  the  ball  hard.     'The police officer is my father'.
           ('The  ball'  is  the  object  of  the   b) The girl is my sister.
           verb, 'kicked').                     c) The boy you're talking about is
           c) The  children,  playfully,           my friend.
              uprooted some flowers around      d) They are our neighbours.
              the  house.  ('Some  flowers'  is
              the  object  of  the  verb,  Note that when we use a noun, noun
              'uprooted').                  phrase or noun clause, after an auxiliary
                                            verb,  it  is  complement  of  subject  of
       -   Noun is object of preposition:  sentence.
           There  are  two  objects,  namely,
           direct  object  (OD)  and  indirect
           object (OI). While the direct object  PRONOUN
           relates  with  the  transitive  verb  Pronoun is a word we use in the place of
           directly, the indirect object does so  noun. Thus, pronoun and noun perform
           indirectly  through  a  preposition.  the same grammatical functions. This is
           Consider the following examples:  why we will not repeat all the details we
           a) Bola  bought  a  car  for  her  discussed in nouns.
               mother. ('Mother' is the indirect
               object).  Note  that  even if  the  CLASSES OF PRONOUN
               sentence  reads,  'Bola  bought
               her  mother  a  car',  'mother'  Personal Pronouns
               would be or is still the indirect  These  pronouns  refer  to  grammatical
               object  or  object  to  the  persons.  There  are  three  persons  in
               preposition, 'for'.          grammar: The first person who is the
           b) The goods arrived from Lagos.  speaker, the second person who is the
               ('Lagos' is the object to 'from').  receiver  or  anyone  or  animal  or  thing
           c) He left for the village yesterday.  spoken  to,  and  the  third  person  is
               ('The  village'  is  the  object  to  anyone, thing or animal spoken about.
               'for').
                                            It is pertinent to understand that a verb
       -   Noun is complement of subject  used with the first person 'I', 'We', must
           of sentence or simply, noun is  be in the plural form. A verb used with
           subject  compliment:  When  we  the second person, 'you' must also be in
           use  a  noun  as  complement  of  the plural form. But any verb used with
           subject, we need to know that both  the third person, 'he' 'she' 'it', must be in
           subject  and  complement  are  the  the singular form. Look at the table for
           same  and  interchangeable.  clarification.
           Consider the following examples:
           a) My father is a police officer. (In
              the sentence, 'police officer' is
              complement of 'my father' the
              subject.  We  can  equally  say,
                                          18]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART FOUR
        Persons            Verb & Predicate   Demonstrative Pronouns
         st
        1 persons                           These  pronouns  are  used  to  direct

        I (singular subject)   do not know him.


        We (plural subject)   do not know him.   attention to a person/persons, a place,

                                            something or things and animals. They
         nd
        2 persons                           are this, that, these and those.
        You (singular subject)  do not know him.  -  This is a book. (Especially when the

        You (plural subject)    do not know him.   book is close to the speaker).

         rd
        3 persons                           -   That  is  a  book.  (Used  when  the
        He                 does not know him.   book  is  not  near  or  close  to  the

        She       singular subjects   does not know him.  speaker).
        It                 does not know him.  -  These are books. (Used when there
        They (plural subject)   do not know him.
                                                are more than one book).
       Note that the plural third person, 'they',  -  Those are books. (Used when the
       agrees with a plural verb, like the first   books are not close to the speaker).
       persons  and  second  persons.  The
       pronouns mentioned in the table above  Reflexive Pronouns
       are all in the subject case. They have  These pronouns are used to show that a
       their object forms as well.          person  or  thing  mentioned  in  a
                                            sentence, actually performed the action.
       First persons:  me (singular object)  They are also classified in to persons like
              us (plural object)            the personal pronouns.
       Second                               First persons – myself, ourselves
       persons:  you  (singular  object,  e.g.  I  Second persons – yourself, yourselves
                gave  you  the  ball  last  Third persons – himself, herself, itself,
                evening).                   themselves

              you (plural object, e.g. I gave  Possessive Pronouns
                y o u   a l l   i n s t r u c t i o n s   These  pronouns  are  used  in  the
                yesterday).                 possessive case without the use of the
                                            apostrophe. Note that noun, when in the
       Third persons:                       possessive  case,  has  apostrophe  and
              him  (singular  object  for  followed with an 's', e.g., John's ball. The
                male/masculine gender).     possessive  pronoun  has  both  the
                                            subject and object forms and classified
              her  (singular  object  for  into persons like the personal pronoun.
                female/feminine gender).
                                            First persons   my (subject singular)
              it  (singular  object  for  neuter          mine (object singular)
              gender).                                    our (subject plural)
                                                          ours (object plural)
              them (plural object form).

                                          19]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART FOUR
                                            Reciprocal Pronouns
       Second persons                       These pronouns reciprocate each other
              your (subject singular)       the way they are used, e.g., each other,
                      yours (object singular)  one another.
                      your (subject plural)
                      yours (object plural)  Indefinite Pronouns
                                            These  pronouns  can  be  used  for  any
       Third persons                        grammatical  person.  E.g.  anyone,  no
       his (subject singular, masculine gender)   one,  someone,  somebody,  everyone,
       her (subject singular, feminine gender)   etc.
       its (subject singular, neuter gender)
       their (subject plural)               VERB
                                            The verb is a word that describes action,
       his – (object singular, masculine)   time  or  tense.  Note  that  tense  is  an
       hers – (object singular, feminine)   agreement between time and action.
       its – (object singular, neuter gender)
       theirs – (object plural)             Verbs  can  broadly  be  classified  into
                                            lexical  and  auxiliary  parts  while  the
       Your ball has fallen into the well.  lexical  verb  can  take  inflections,  the
       The ball is yours.                   auxiliary verb is a helping verb.


       His ball has fallen into the well.   Auxiliary Verbs
       The ball is his.                     These verbs are made up of the primary
                                            auxiliaries and the modals or anomalous
       Her doll is new.                     finites.
       The doll is hers.
                                            Primary Auxiliary Verbs
       Its kids are playing.                be, is, am, are, being, been, do, does,
       The kids are its.                    did, done, have, has, had.

       Their home village is quite far.     Modal Auxiliaries/Anomalous Finites
       The village is theirs.               can,  could,  shall,  should,  may,  might,
                                            dare, ought to, need, used to, must, will,
       Interrogative Pronouns               would.
       These  pronous  are  used  to  ask
       questions. Who, why, which, etc.     Active Verb
                                            When  an  active  verb  is  used  in  a
       Relative Pronouns                    sentence, the subject of the sentence
       These  pronouns  relate  a  piece  of  performs the action.
       information to a noun. They are, who,  Examples:
       which, that, whose, whom, etc.       -   The boy cut the tree down.
                                            -   He locked the door firmly.
                                            -   Lanre drove the car slowly.
                                          20]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART FOUR
       Passive Verb                         The Present Tense
       When  a  passive  verb  is  used  in  a  Any  action  that  takes  place  in  the
       sentence, the subject of that sentence  present time is said to be in the present
       becomes an object.                   tense. For example;
                                            -   I write a lot.
       Examples:                            -   I write every day.
       -   The tree was cut down.
       -   The door was locked firmly.      -   The Present Progressive Tense:
       -   The car was driven slowly.           This is used to show that while a
                                                person speaks, the action is talking
       Note that we know the doer of an action   about is going on or taking place.
       in a sentence with an active verb but do   E.g., I am writing now.
       not  know  the  doer  of  an  action  in  a
       sentence with a passive verb.        -   The Present Perfect Tense: This
                                                shows complete action. E.g., I have
       Transitive and Intransitive Verbs        written the letter.


       Transitive Verb                      -   T h e   P r e s e n t   P e r f e c t
       Any  verb  that  takes  an  object  in  a   Progressive  Tense:  This  is  a
       sentence  is  a  transitive  verb.  For   complete but on going action. E.g., I
       examples:                                have  been  writing  since  this
       -   They pushed the car down the road.   morning.
           ('pushed'  is  the  transitive  verb
           which takes the object, 'car').  The Past Tense
       -   The  woman  stirred  some  soup  in  This tense indicates past action. E.g., I
           the  pot.  ('stirred'  is  the  transitive  wrote a letter yesterday.
           verb  while  the  object  it  takes  is  -  Past  Progressive  Tense:  This
           'some soup').                        tense shows simultaneous actions.
                                                For example;
       Intransitive Verbs                       a) I was writing but he was singing
       This  verb  does  not  take  an  object   b) I was writing when he called.
       because it does not need it. Consider the
       following:                           -   The Past Perfect Tense: In the
       -   The sun shines everyday.             past perfect tense, two actions take
       -   She slept very well last night.      place but not simultaneously. E.g., I
       -   In the past, slaves suffered much.   had  written  the  letter  when  dad
                                                called me.

       TENSES                               -   The  Past  Perfect  Progressive
       Tenses  are  used  to  indicate  or  show   Tense: This tense is used to show
       action  and  time.  It  is  a  relationship   past  complete  action  though  in
       between action and time.                 progression.  E.g.,  I  had  been
                                                writing when the rain started.
                                          21]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART FOUR
       The Future Tense                        Regular and Irregular Verbs
       This tense shows an action that is about
       to take place. Any action planned to take  Regular Verbs
       place is in the future. In this case, the  These  are  verbs  that  take  the  'ed'
       anomalous verb, 'shall' or 'will' must be  inflection or ending to form past tense
       used, depending on the person.       and past participle. This means that the
                                            past tense form of a regular verb is the
       Examples:                            same  as  its  past  participle  form.
       -   I shall write a letter tomorrow.   However,  they  are  not  the  same  in
       -   You will write a note for the student.  application. Study the table below:



                                             Present Tense  Past Tense   Past Participle
       -   The Future Progressive Tense:     Believe     Believed   Believed

           This tense anticipates a progressive   Travel   Travelled   Travelled

           action. Example, I shall be writing a   Clime   Climed   Climed
                                             Repair        Repaired   Repaired
           letter tomorrow.                  Receive     Received  Received

                                             Pull        Pulled    Pulled

       -   The  Future  Perfect  Tense:      Push        Pushed    Pushed

                                             Remove      Removed   Removed
           Although  a  future  action  is   Return      Returned   Returned

           anticipated,  it  is  assumed  to  be   Control  Controlled   Controlled

           completed. E.g., I shall have written   Renovate   Renovated   Renovated
           the  letter  by  the  time  you  return
           tomorrow.                        Irregular Verbs
                                            These verbs do not have any uniform
       -   The Future Perfect Progressive  and are not regular in form. Study the
           Tense: This happens to be the most  table below:
           complex  of  all  tenses.  It  is  a   Present Tense  Past Tense   Past Participle


           c o m p l e t e   a c t i o n ,   y e t ,   i n    Give     Gave  Given

                                             Ride        Rode      Ridden
           progression,  all  anticipated  to
                                             Drive       Drove        Driven
           happen in the future. E.g., By this   Write     Wrote   Written

           time  tomorrow,  I  shall  have  been   Take     Took   Taken

           writing the letter.               Break       Broke     Broken

                                             See         Saw       Seen
                                             Sleep       Slept     Sle  pt
           I shall have been writing the letter   Put     Put        Put
           by the time the crucial match begins   Cut     Cut      Cut

                                             Eat         Ate       Eaten
           tomorrow.                         Sit         Sat        Sat
                                             Read        Read        Read
                                             Build       Built     Built
                                             Run         Ran         Run
                                             Come        Came       Come
                                             Know        Knew         Known
                                          22]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART FOUR
       EXERCISE 1
                                            -   Adverbs  of  Degree:  These
       a) Make sentences with some regular      adverbs show the level of an action.
           and irregular verbs in the present   E.g., high, low, fast, slow, etc.
           tense,  past  tense  and  in  the  past
           participle.                      -   Adverbs  of  Concession:  These
       b) What are the functions of verbs?      adverbs  are  sometimes  used  as
       c)  What  is  the  relationship  between   linking  words.  They  appear  to  be
           noun and pronoun?                    separated from the sentence where
       d) Make  sentences  with  all  the       they  used  but  not.  E.g.,  however,
           personal pronouns you know.          since, although, etc.
       e) What is tense?
                                            -   Adverbs of Place: These adverbs
       EXERCISE 2                               tells us the place of an action. E.g.,
                                                here, there, where, etc.
       Identify  the  grammatical  function  in
       each of the following:               -   Adverbs  of  Frequency:  These
       a) I know Obi.                           adverbs tell us the number of times
       b) He left me at home.                   actions take place. E.g., sometimes,
       c) My brother has travelled.             always, often, seldom, rare, etc.
       d) He is my friend.
       e) The  stadium  is  filled  to  capacity  -  Adverbs  of  Purpose:  These
           already.                             adverbs modify  the  verb they  are
                                                used with when they lay emphasis
                                                on the objective of certain actions.
       ADVERBS                                  E.g., therefore, so, since, etc.
       Adverbs are  words  that  modify  verbs.
       They tell us when, how, etc, if an action.  -  Adverbs  of  Condition:  These
       Study the classes of adverbs discussed   adverbs show that an action is not
       here.                                    possible  without  taking  care  of  a
                                                condition. E.g., unless, until, if, etc.
       -   Adverbs of Time: These adverbs
           modify verbs when they show the
           time actions are taken. Examples,  EXERCISE
           every day, now, when, etc.
           a) I go to school everyday.      1. What is adverb?
           b) She  dances  only  when  she  is  2. How is it used in a sentence?
              told.                         3. What is an adverbial?
                                            4. Give five (5) examples of adverbs of
       -   Adverbs of Reason: Every action      time.
           we take has a reason. E.g., because,  5. Make  five  (5)  sentences  with
           since, as a result, etc.             adverbs of degree.

                                          23]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART FOUR
       PREPOSITIONS                         it is correct to say,
       Prepositions are a part of speech which   I  live  at  Asokoro  in  Abuja  or  I  live  in
       indicates  position,  the  position  of   Asokoro.
       someone,  a  place,  or  something.   I live at Karmo.
       Prepositions show place, direction, etc.   I live at Gwagwa.
       Consider the following examples: in, on,   I live in Wuse.
       along, by, to, towards, forward, inward,
       inside, outside, onto, into, at, up, down,   Study more examples below:
       over, under, beneath, etc.           a) My  friend  is  on  admission  at  this
                                                hospital.
       How to use the prepositions 'in', 'at' and   b) Bello works in this hospital.
       'on'                                 c) My  uncle  works  in  the  Ministry  of
                                                Agriculture.
       We  use  'in'  to  mean  an  enclosed  or   d) I believe in God.
       partially enclosed place.            e) He stared long at the board without
                                                any comprehension.
       We say, 'The man in the street', not 'The
       man on the street', because a street is
       partially  enclosed.  Thus,  The  children
       playing in the street look hungry.
                                            EXERCISE
       The woman selling 'bolei' in the street is
       business-like.                       Find  the  right  adverbial  particle  to
                                            complete each sentence below:
       I live in this street.               1. The lizard dashed ______ the hot
                                                tarmac.
       My house is in this street, (Not on this   2. The ball flew ______ the goal posts.
       street).                             3. The lazy boy tagged ___________
                                            4. He looked askance _____ the police
       We say a person is either on a hot seat or   inspector.
       in the hot seat, depending whether the   5. The secretary _____ the desk is my
       seat has arms rest or not. If the seat has   friend.
       arm rest, we say, a person is in the hot   6. As I am talking to you, Danjuma is
       seat. But if the seat does not have arm   walking _______ the gate.
       rest, then, we say, the person is on the   7.  The man stood ________ his friend
       hot seat.                                as a witness __________ the case.
                                            8. He  revealed  their  secrets  ______
       In terms of living in or at a place, a lot   me.
       depends on whether the place is small or   9. I prefer beans and plantain _______
       large.  For  example,  Dele  lives  in   rice and beans.
       Gwagwalada (not at Gwagwalada). But   10. The  girl  has,  undoubtedly  taken
       Dele lives at Gwagwalada in Abuja (in    _____ her mother _____ manners.
       terms of comparison). In the same way,
                                          24]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART FOUR
       ADJECTIVES                           CONJUNCTIONS
       Adjectives are words that modify nouns   These  words  join  words,  phrases,
       and/or  pronouns.  They  state  certain   clauses and so on. Conjunctions make
       qualities in nouns or pronouns. We have   two  simple  sentences  a  compound
       attributive  and  predicative  adjectives.   sentence.
       When an adjective precede the noun it
       modifies,  it  is  an attributive adjective.   We  have  coordinating  conjunctions
       E.g., she is a young woman but if the   which  join  similar  ideas  in  separate
       noun being modified is made to come   sentences. For example:
       before the adjective, then the adjective   -  I love my teacher
       is  a  predicative  adjective.  E.g.,  the   -  He is good.
       woman is old.
                                            To turn the simple sentences above to a
       Adjectives of Degree                 compound  sentence,  we  need  to
       Adjectives have three levels or degrees.   introduce  a  conjunction,  like  because,
       Look at the table below:             after all, the idea in the first sentence is
        Positive    Comparative  Superlative   as  a  result  of  what  is  in  the  second

        Long      Longer      Longest       sentence.
        Tall     Taller       Tallest       I love my teacher because he is good.
        Bright   Brighter     Brightest
        Dark     Darker       Darkest
        Thick     Thicker     Thickest      We  also  have  the  subordinating
        Thin     Thinner      Thinnest      conjunction.  This  conjunction  joins
        Tough    Tougher      Toughest      different ideas.
        Loud     Louder       Loudest       I love my teacher
                                            She is not good.
       Note that there are regular and irregular
       adjectives. The examples of adjectives   We  need  a  conjunction  that  is
       in the table above are regular adjectives.   subordinating  to  join  the  two  simple
       The  irregular  adjective  does  not  have   sentences above.
       any  uniform,  e.g.  much,  more,  most,   I  love  my  teacher,  though  she  is  not
       bad, worse, worst, good, better, best.   good.

       Note  that  two  comparative  adjectives   There are also correlative conjunctions.
       should not be used in a sentence, e.g.   These  conjunctions  are  used  with  the
       This classroom is more better than that   concord rule of proximity, which is, of
       classroom.                           two  items  that  make  subject  of
                                            sentence,  the  one  nearer  the  verb
       EXERCISE                             agrees with the verb in number. Thus, if
       1.  Construct a table and make a list of   the item is singular, the verb is singular
           ten  (10)  irregular  adjectives   or  plural  if  the  item  is  plural.  The
           showing their positive, comparative   conjunctions  are,  either  and  neither.
           and superlative degrees.         Although they called conjunctions, they
       2. Make a sentence with each of them.   do not function as other conjunctions.
                                          25]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART FOUR
       Either Nkechi or Okafor is brilliant. (We   EXERCISE
       don't  know  who  is  brilliant  between
       them).                               1. What is conjunction?

       Neither  Nkechi  nor  Okafor  is  brilliant.   2. Join  the  following  pairs  to  make
       (Both are not brilliant).                compound sentences:
                                                a) I want to travel.
       There  are  also  semi-conjunctions.     b) I have no money.
       Examples  of  semi-conjunctions  are,
       together with, in addition to, as well as,   a) It is quite dark.
       etc.                                     b) Ada went out without any lamp.

       The  boy,  together  with  the  girl  is   a) She  passed  the  exams
       industrious. (The boy is hardworking).      excellently.
                                                b) She was weeping.
       Talatu, as well as the other girls, is here
       to see the principal.                    a) I have the strength.
                                                b) I will not work.

                                                a) He ate with relish.
                                                b) The soup is palatable.

                                                a) We trust each other.
                                                b) We are friends.





























                                          26]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART FIVE
       LITERATURE                               is to say, it teaches wisdom, morals,
                                                patience,  hardworking,  honesty,
       For the purpose of this study, literature   kindness,  godliness,  etc.  In  other
       is made up of prose, drama and poetry.   words,  folktales  enrich  societal
       We shall discuss them each in detail.    values.  Examples  of  folktales  are
                                                stories of the dog and the hare, the
       PROSE                                    tortoise  and  the  elephant,  etc.
       Prose means continuous writing. Every    Animals'  characters  are  given
       work of prose has an important element   human  attributes  to  enable  them
       which is narration, no matter the form of   communicates well.
       prose. Prose is made up of fiction and
       non-fiction.                         -   Mythology:  Myths  are  also
                                                folkloric in nature. They are legends
       PROSE AS FICTION                         or stories about a people's origin.
       Fiction is any creative work that contains   Although they are not facts, some of
       imaginary  characters  and  events  as   them are true. Myths can hardly be
       opposed to reality.                      separated  from  legend  because
                                                they are the same. Examples are:
               TYPES OF FICTION                 The Yoruba Myth, The Greek Myth,
                                                The Tiv Myth, etc.
       -   Novel: This is the longest prose. It
           contains many characters, themes,    It should be born in mind that some
           plots, etc. Examples of novels are:   legends  are  themselves  facts
           Things  Fall  Apart,  No  Longer  At   through and through. They do not
           Ease,  The  Man  Died,  The  Bottled   bear any myth at all. For example:
           Leopard, The Potter's Wheel, etc.    The Story of Morenike is a popular
                                                Yoruba  legend.  The  origin  of  the
       -   Novella/Novellete: This is a very    Hausa State is also a popular legend
           short  prose  work.  It  has  few    amongst a people who talk about
           characters, few plots, themes, etc.   original Hausas and the ones that
           Examples  of  novelletes  are:  Dizy   are  not  part  of  the  original  or
           Angel, Eze Goes To School, Akpan     legitimate  Hausa  States.  Thus,
           and The Smugglers, etc.              there  are  legends  that  do  not
                                                contain myths at all.
       -   Short  Story:  The  short  story  is
           much  shorter  than  the  novella  or   PROSE AS NON-FICTION
           novellete. It can have one or two   Non-fictional works are based on facts.
           characters  and  one,  two  or  more   They are not works of creativity. Where,
           plots.  Short  stories  are  always  in   however, imaginary characters are used
           collections.                     in a work of non-fiction like a textbook,
                                            such usage is to illustrate a point.
       -   Folktale:  This  is  part  of  cultural
           folklore and is usually didactic, that
                                          27]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART FIVE
       Examples of non-fiction are textbooks,   -  Character  and  Characterization:
       biography, autobiography, memoir, etc.   A character is a person or an animal
                                                in  a  story;  myth  or  legend,  who
       -   Textbooks: A book on any subject     plays a role, whether important or
           matter for students' and teachers'   unimportant. Thus, we have major
           use is a textbook.                   and  minor  characters.  Major
                                                characters appear more often and
       -   Biography:  An  account  of  a       undertake  more  demanding  tasks
           person's  life,  written  by  another   than minor characters.
           person  is  known  as  biography.
           People usually tell the public about   Characterization is the development
           great characters or public figures by   of  characters  in  a  story.  The
           writing  about  their  birth,  family,   development of a character is aided
           academic training, etc.              by the character's traits. Things like
                                                a  person's  emotions,  beliefs,
       -   Autobiography:  When  a  person      principles,  thought,  pattern,
           writes about his own life, then such   desires,  fear  and  so  on,  go  to
           work  is  an  autobiography.  Such   making  a  character.  They  are  the
           work  usually  results  from  public   elements that help us know who a
           demand.                              character is and who is not.


       -   Memoir:  This  is  a  collection  of  a   -  Setting:  Setting  could  be
           person's experiences over a period   geographical in which case it refers
           of time and published to meet public   to location or simply, the locale of an
           demand.  For  example:  Soyinka's    event. Every story takes place at a
           Memoir, Achebe's Memoir, etc.        place. Here, it is helpful for a place
                                                of event to be real, a real place. It
          CHARACTERISTICS OF PROSE              helps  make  a  work  of  fiction,  for
                                                instance, real.
       -   Theme:  Every  prose  work  –
           whether  fiction  or  non-fiction  is   We  also  have  cultural  setting  –
           made up of themes. A theme is a      language,  socio-political  setting,
           subject matter on which a work of    which is the country or the socio-
           prose is based. A general theme can   political group the story is about.
           be broken down into sub-themes.
                                            v.  Style and Diction: The style of an
       -   Plot:  Plot  is  a  distinct  event,   author shows whether his work is
           especially,  in  a  work  of  fiction.  A   difficult  to  understand  or  quite
           novel, novellete, a short or folktale   simple.  Diction  is  the  choice  of
           cannot exist without plot. We have   words used to tell a story. It's the
           tight and loose plots.               diction that tells the reader the style
                                                an  author  used  in  his  work.  If  a
                                                writer  is  mindful  of  his  audience
                                          28]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART FIVE
       which  made  up  of  technocrats  or               DRAMA
       intellectual  people,  then,  he  uses  an   Drama  means  a  performance  that  is
       elevated  language  to  suite  that   staged. This is usually done in front of an
       audience. But if the work is for children,   audience.
       then,  the  style  is  simple.  Again,  an
       author may use a general diction if his   SOME DRAMATIC ELEMENTS
       audience cuts across the general public,   -  Settings
       after  all,  the  purpose  of  writing  is  to   -  Plots
       communicate an intended message.     -   Costume
                                            -   Characters
                                            -   Stage
       EXERCISE                             -   Stage direction

       1.  What is prose?                   TYPES OF DRAMA
                                            -   Tragedy
       2.  Mention the parts prose is made of.  -  Comedy
                                            -   Tragi-comedy
       3.  State the differences among novel,   -  Farce
           novella and short story.         -   Satire
                                            -   Melodrama
       4.  How is legend different from myth?
                                            POETRY
       5.  Mention and discuss the elements   Poetry  is  a  collection  of  lines  that
           of prose.                        represents a person's emotion. It is a
                                            beautiful arrangement of ideas in lines
                                            of well-chosen words.
                                                    TYPES OF POETRY


                                            -   Satire:  This  is  a  poem  or  any
                                                literary work that criticizes a society
                                                constructively.


                                            -   Epic: This is a poem with historical
                                                element.  It  is  usually  written  and
                                                dedicated to a great man.

                                            -   Ballad:  This  is  a  very  long  poem
                                                that  is  sung.  It  is  about  the
                                                achievements of a warrior.

                                            -   Narrative Poem: This poem tells a
                                                story. It is usually very long.
                                          29]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[ENGLISH LANGUAGE PART FIVE
       -   Epigram:  This  is  a  short  writing  -  Irony:  This  is  an  indirect
           poem.                                statement. It alludes to the truth or
                                                reality,  always.  Making  a  general
       -   Valedictory Poem: This poem is       statement such as, 'Someone here
           used to bid a person farewell or is   is hardly present in class,' instead of
           simply  written  to  mourn  a  dead   talking  to  the  person  directly,  is
           person.                              ironical.

       -   Pastoral Poem: This poem depicts  -  Euphemism: This figure of speech
           agricultural and rural activities.   makes  use  of  gentle  words  to
                                                express harsh reality. For example:
       ELEMENTS OF POETRY                       The  man  kicked  the  bucket  early
       -   Lines                                this morning. 'He is a gentleman of
       -   Rhyme/beat                           the underworld.’
       -   Stanza
       -   Rhythm
       -   Character
       -   Diction                          EXERCISE

       FIGURE OF SPEECH                     1. State  the  parts  that  make  up
       These  are  literary  devices  used  in   Literature.
       literary  work  to  make  it  intellectually
       beautiful. Study the following:      2. What is drama?

       -   Metaphor: This is a direct way of  3. What is the importance of drama?
           making comparism. John was a lion
           in the battle field. The boy is an ape.   4. What is poetry?

       -   Simile:  This  is  an  indirect  5. Discuss  five  (5)  figures  of  speech
           comparism. For example: She is as    you know.
           lousy  as  a  bee.  She  looks  like  a
           queen.


       -   Paradox:  This  is  a  statement  of
           contradiction  that  contains  some
           truth. For example: The boy is the
           father of the man.

       -   Oxymoron:  It  is  a  figure  of
           contradiction where two words with
           opposite meanings are placed side
           by side. For example: Truth is bitter
           sweet.
                                          30]]></page></pages></Search>